<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Post-rsses on The Scientific Explanation</title>
    <link>https://sciexpln.github.io/post/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Post-rsses on The Scientific Explanation</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Powered by [Hugo](//gohugo.io). Theme by [PPOffice](http://github.com/ppoffice).</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 13:34:45 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://sciexpln.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Vitamin B17 does not Cure Cancer</title>
      <link>https://sciexpln.github.io/2016/12/27/vitamin-b17-does-not-cure-cancer</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 13:34:45 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sciexpln.github.io/2016/12/27/vitamin-b17-does-not-cure-cancer</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As with many many WhatsApp forwards, I received another message outlining a miracle cure. This time, as quite often, for curing cancer. This message said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The word called cancer is a lie…You might not believe this but cancer is not a disease; it is a business.Cancer consists of only a deficiency of vitamin B17. It is nothing else.
Cancer has become widespread; it has affected the old, young, baby and everyone.Sharing this wonderful post will expose many of the hidden hands of the world’s manipulators and annoy them.Do you know that the book “World Without Cancer” has up till now been prevented from being translated into many world languages?
Know this: there is no disease called cancer. Cancer consists of only a deficiency of vitamin B17. It is nothing else.
Avoid chemotherapy, surgery and or taking medicines with strong side effects.
You would recall that in the past, quite a large number of seamen lost their life to a named disease (scurvy); a disease that took the life of numerous people as well. And a number of people got an enormous income from it. Afterwards, it was discovered that scurvy was just a deficiency of vitamin C. That means it wasn’t a disease (illness).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cancer is also just like that! The colonizing world and the enemies of humanity established the cancer industry and made it into a business. from which they earn billions in income.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The cancer industry flourished after world war II. To fight cancer, all these delays, details and enormous expenditures are not needed. They only go to line the pockets of colonizers, especially since the cure for the condition was found long ago.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The prevention and cure of cancer will be obtained simply through the following strategies:
Those who have cancer should first try to know what cancer is. Do not panic! You should investigate the condition.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nowadays does anyone die of an illness called scurvy? No. Because it gets cured.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Since cancer is only a deficiency of vitamin B17, eating 15 to 20 pieces of apricot stone/nucleus (fruit stone) everyday is enough.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eat wheat bud (wheat sprouts). Wheat bud is a miraculous anti-cancer medicine. It is a rich source of liquid oxygen and the strongest anti-cancer matter named laetrile. This matter is present in the fruit stone of apple and is the extracted form of vitamin B17 (Amygdalin).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The American medicinal industry has started implementing the law forbidding laetrile production. This medicine is being manufactured in Mexico and gets smuggled into USA.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dr. Harold W. Manner, in a book named “Death of Cancer” has stated that the success of cancer treatment with laetrile is as high as above 90%.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sources of Amygdalin (Vitamin B17)
The foods containing vitamin B17 include the following:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The fruit stone or grain(seed) of fruits. This contains the highest amount of vitamin B17 in nature. This includes fruit stone of apple, apricot, peach, pear, and prune (dried plum).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Common beans, corns(grains), which include bean, lentil sprout (lentil bud) Lima (Lima beans) and pea.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kernels: Bitter Almond (Richest source of vitamin B-17 in nature) and Indian almond.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mulberries: almost all mulberries such as black mulberry, blueberry, raspberry and strawberry.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seeds (Grains): sesame and linseed (seed of linen/flax seed).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Groats of oats, barley, brown rice, groats of block wheat, linseed, millet and rye.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This vitamin is found in grains and fruit stones of apricot, brewer’s yeast, rough rice (paddy) and sweetmeat pumpkin.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;List of Anti-Cancer Foods: Apricots (kernels/seeds), seeds from other fruits like apples, cherries, peaches, prunes, plums, pears, Lima beans, Fava beans, Wheatgrass, Almonds, Raspberries, Elderberries, Strawberries, Blackberries, Blueberries, Buckwheat, Sorghum, Barley, Millet, Cashews, Macadamia nuts, Bean sprouts, all are the highest sources of absorbable vitamin B17.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ingesting dish washing liquids (used in the kitchen) and hand washing liquid (used in the restroom) is the main cancer causing factor so your eating of them should be restricted.You will surely say that we do not eat them!
However, you daily wash your hands with hand washing liquid and wash your plates with dish washing liquid.The liquid is absorbed and will not leave the plate with washing. When cooking or eating food, the soap in the plate or dish gets attached to the hot food and so we end up eating the dish washing liquid with our food. Even if you rinse the plate hundreds of times, that will be of no use.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But the solution is to pour half of the dishwashing liquid and hand washing liquid and top it up with vinegar.
It is as simple as that.Do not eat blood cancer causing agents and also save your family from this danger.Similarly, seriously desist from washing vegetables with even a few drops of dishwashing liquid because irrespective of how much you would rinse them, the chemicals would have already entered the tissues of the vegetable and will not get rinsed away.Instead, soak fruits and vegetables with salt and then rinse with water. And to keep them fresh, add vinegar.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please share this post with others so they can also benefit from the information.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original source of this information is &lt;a href=&#34;http://newsrescue.com/secret-uncovered-cancer-not-disease-business/#ixzz4LjhzhrTJ&#34;&gt;this website&lt;/a&gt;, but since this I&amp;rsquo;ve copy pasted the entire page here, let&amp;rsquo;s not click on it and give them any more ad revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, picking this apart point by point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cancer is a deficiency of a vitamin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the official website of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cancer.gov&#34;&gt;National Cancer Institute (NCI)&lt;/a&gt;, cancer is defined as:&lt;em&gt;Cancer is the name given to a collection of related diseases. In all types of cancer, some of the body’s cells begin to divide without stopping and spread into surrounding tissues.&lt;/em&gt; Its genesis is outlined as: &lt;em&gt;Cancer is a genetic disease—that is, it is caused by changes to genes that control the way our cells function, especially how they grow and divide.&lt;/em&gt; These genetic changes come both, as inheritance from parents as well as due to errors in cell division in the body or DNA modifications as a result of certain exposures. There are more than 100 types of cancer, and saying that all cancer results from a vitamin deficiency is not a well-established mechanism for cancer. There are many known genetic as well as external carcinogenic causes of cancer, which are not deficiency related. Also, even if there were some grounding to this theory, &amp;ldquo;Vitamin B17&amp;rdquo; does not satisfy this as explained in point 2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;That vitamin is vitamin B17, which is actually Amygdalin, also called laterile&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam&#34;&gt;PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board&lt;/a&gt;, an arm of the National Cancer Institute with editorial independence from NCI, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmedhealth/PMH0032851/#!po=83.0097&#34;&gt;reviewed&lt;/a&gt; the claims regarding laterile. According to the board, laterile is another name for the compound amygdalin,  which is incorrectly called vitamin B17, as this definition is not approved by the Committee on Nomenclature of the American Institute of Nutrition Vitamins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paragraph is a tl;dr summary of the PDQ article linked above, so, for the intrepid souls that way inclined, the references to the corresponding original studies can be found linked within that article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laterile is not a natural product but a semisynthetically prepared chemical, which has different chemical compositions in USA (mandelonitrile-beta-glucuronide) and Mexico(mandelonitrile beta-D-gentiobioside). The proposed mechanism for laterile acting against cancer suggests that it releases hydrogen cyanide, which attacks the cancer cells. Oral ingestion of chemically synthesized laterile has been shown to result in higher rates of cyanide poisioning than injection. Section 3 of the PDQ article outlines how no scientific or pre-clinical study has been able to establish increase in animal survival on treating with laterile. Instead, at higher levels of laterile concentration, toxicity from the cyanide was observed. No clear well documented double blind trial of laterile without interference from other treatments like radiation or chemotherapy has ever been conducted. In most otherwise evaluated patients, small observed symptomatic benefits of laterile did not persist. Side effects of cyanide poisoning were observed in the patients being treated. All in all, there is no solid evidence for the effectiveness of laterile as a treatment for cancer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cancer rates exploded after WWII&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2927383/&#34;&gt;The history of cancer research&lt;/a&gt; show studies have been carried out for over 3000 years, the oldest documented case being as far back in time as 1500BC in Egypt. An indepth history of cancer research has been very well documented by the Harvard Physician &lt;a href=&#34;http://siddharthamukherjee.com/&#34;&gt;Dr. Siddharth Mukherjee&lt;/a&gt; in his book: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Emperor-All-Maladies-Biography-Cancer/dp/1439170916&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Emperor of all Maladies - A Biography of Cancer&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. (As an aside, I would totally recommend this book). It is a fascinating read describing all the research into cancer over the past 3000, but mainly over the past 200 years. Which means cancer was being studied for a long time before world war II. The recent explosion in cancer rates is due to (among a lot of other factors):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A better understanding of cancer, leading to better diagnosis of the condition in recent time and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An increased human life span, which gives longer time for mutation based diseases like cancer or degenerative diseases like Alzheimers and Parkinsons to develop. A couple of hundred years ago, most people were killed off by tuberculosis and small pox waaay before they could get old enough to develop cancer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Possible synthesis and ejection into the environment, of potential carcinogens through certain industrial processes, or known factors like smoking, which have also risen over the past couple of centuries of industrialization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wheat bud/sprouts is a rich source of liquid oxygen and the strongest anti-cancer matter named laetrile&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liquid oxygen has a boiling point of $-182.96^{\circ} C$ at atmospheric pressure, so it would be really hard for any plant to store it that way under normal biological conditions. The properties of laterile (or lack thereof) has already been discussed in point 2 above.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The therapy of Harold W. Manner&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The American Cancer Society leaves this &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/store/10.3322/canjclin.36.3.185/asset/185_ftp.pdf;jsessionid=F8FCB509FB098B151495A54B5709A7F8.f02t02?v=1&amp;amp;t=ix3ozvms&amp;amp;s=7ddd31d5a990cee9280ccfb07e4322caffa1eae4&#34;&gt;warning&lt;/a&gt; about Dr. Harold W. Manner:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After careful study of the literature and other information available to it, the American Cancer Society has found no evidence that treatment with the Metabolic Cancer Therapy of Harold W. Manner, PhD, results in objective benefit in the treatment of cancer in human beings. Lacking such evidence, the American Cancer Society would strongly urge individuals with cancer not to participate in treatment with the Metabolic Cancer Therapy of Harold W. Manner, PhD.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, it is definitely possible to think that this is just another example of the medical establishment trying to suppress the man who has the truth so that they can make tons of money for themselves, but I would be inclined to take the people who have studied the evidence seriously.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cancer from dish washing liquid and soap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t even know what to say here. They don’t list any specific ingredient which they think is cancer causing, making it impossible to refute other than to say, the ingredients for dish soap are listed on the back, and none of them seem to be known carcinogens. Also, I am at a complete loss to understand how vinegar (primarily acetic acid) can somehow stop the carcinogenic effect of whatever mystery cancer chemical it is that dish washing liquid contains.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scientific, medical, and pharmaceutical establishment has occasionally got things wrong. Sometimes really wrong (The &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thalidomide#Birth_defects_crisis&#34;&gt;thalidomide tragedy&lt;/a&gt; comes to mind). However, when they realized it, they have corrected their mistakes, either voluntarily, or due to enforcement of strict government regulation. However, a wholesale disregard for the entire scientific establishment, and claiming a persecution of some type of lone wolves like Dr. Harold W. Manner who have &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;the truth&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; seems like a disingenuous approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are thousands of labs in research institutes across the planet working hard to try to understand the causes of cancer and looking for cures, starting from looking for possible genetic markers using computational approaches through gene editing technologies like CRISPR/CAS9 which could be used for gene editing to prevent cancer to trying to improve the existing chemotherapy and radiation therapy to make it more focussed and targeted, to prevent collateral damage of non-cancerous cells to novel drug delivery systems for precise delivery of the drugs of choice, and many many more. Just seems a bit reductionist to claim that, in the face of one of the most complex biological problems that science has faced, the experts who spend years trying to understand it are either too stupid to figure it out and this one genius has all the answers, or even worse, that the experts are all lying in order to keep on lining their fat pockets, and have instituted a witch hunt against the one person with integrity who is trying to bring truth out to the world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind - Yuval Noah Harari</title>
      <link>https://sciexpln.github.io/2016/12/11/sapiens-a-brief-history-of-humankind---yuval-noah-harari</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Dec 2016 14:29:12 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sciexpln.github.io/2016/12/11/sapiens-a-brief-history-of-humankind---yuval-noah-harari</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sciexpln.github.io/images/sapiens-cover.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Sapiens-Humankind-Yuval-Noah-Harari/dp/0062316095&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a book by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ynharari.com/&#34;&gt;Yuval Noah Harari&lt;/a&gt;, an Israeli historian, who is a professor of History at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem.
Sharing a spirit with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jareddiamond.org/Jared_Diamond/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Jared Diamond&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; masterpiece &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Guns-Germs-Steel-Fates-Societies/dp/0393317552&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guns, Germs and Steel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sapiens&lt;/em&gt; is an in depth survey of the development of humans as a species, broadly outlined by three major &amp;ldquo;Revolutions&amp;rdquo; that characterized the &amp;ldquo;cultural evolution&amp;rdquo; of humanity.
These developments have been characterized by the Cognitive Revolution, the Agricultural Revolution, and the Scientific Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Cognitive Revolution&lt;/strong&gt;
This step in the development of &lt;em&gt;Homo Sapiens&lt;/em&gt; is characterized by the development of thinking. The author outlines the distinction of &lt;em&gt;Homo Sapiens&lt;/em&gt; from other species of humans like Neanderthals, Denisovans, and &lt;em&gt;Homo soloensis&lt;/em&gt;. The development of language, and the sharing of information, via the medium of narrative tales conferred upon &lt;em&gt;sapiens&lt;/em&gt; a unique survival advantage. Remembering and communicating information about both, a food source as well as potential danger helped the survival of our species immeasurably, rising above the need to communicate this information through our genome, as all other species had had to, up until that point. While he suggests that the forager and hunter gatherer had a better quality of life than the bonded serf of the age of agriculture, he provides caveats indicating that the flip side of such a society was a strong survival of the fittest narrative, without any support of the old and infirm. &lt;em&gt;Sapiens&lt;/em&gt;, he also points out, have been uniquely the most destructive species ever know, even in the pre-historic and pre-agricultural times, where entire animal species have been shown to be wiped out within relatively short periods of our arrival in those areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Agricultural Revolution&lt;/strong&gt;
Rather surprisingly (to me) Harari suggests that the agricultural revolution was a non-optimal step for our species. Restriction in variety in our diet resulting from only a few crops being grown in an area and overpopulation resulting from the availaiblity of an abundant (although of limited variety) food source, are, according to Harari the ill effects of agriculture. Establishment of kingdoms, and creation of laws were the natural fallout of the gathering of large groups of &lt;em&gt;sapiens&lt;/em&gt; in small areas which were suitable for farming. This, according to the author, resulted in disease spread in the form of epidemics, which the sparsly populated foragers did not face, as well as injustice of the rulers over the ruled, as a result of the establishment of a system of power. Writing, however, developed as a natural consequence of needing to overcome memory in the interactions of such large groups of people congregating at one site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Unification of Humanity&lt;/strong&gt;
The three biggest unifiers of humanity, the author posits, are Money, Empire, and Religion. The development of money over trust and barter was inevitable as a result of large numbers of strangers interacting with each other, having to exchange goods and services of vastly varying and to some extent unquantifiable value. This led to the establishment of currency, which was the first unifier. The program of empire, and its justification via the desire to &amp;ldquo;spread law, values, ideals and culture&amp;rdquo; was another unifier of peoples, who felt they shared a goal, as a result of being part of the same empire. Religion, of course is well understood as both a unifying and dividing force, and its evolution can be traced from the earliest forms of Animism, via the various Polytheisms to the current Monotheist, Dualist, and Polytheist religions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Scientific Revolution&lt;/strong&gt;
The unique admission of our ignorance of all natural systems, according to Harari, was (and still is) a major driving force for the scientific enterprise. Empire building was a major driving force for science, as the endevours of exploration and conquest drove the technology required. Similarly, capitalism and the economy were major drivers for science, as newer means of production were direct gateways towards the creation of wealth. An interesting consequence of the scientific and industrial revolution has been discussed in terms of the dismantling of the family. Contrary to the current narrative, the author does not necessarily think that this is a bad thing since it also brings with it protection of all peoples by the state. New imagined bonds of nationalism, consumerism, as well as political ideologies are created within individuals, further binding them into the larger whole of humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end, Harari goes (in my opinion) more from the realm of well founded observations based on the past, to speculative predictions about the future. He admits as much, that his predictions are purely speculative. However, they shine an interesting light onto the possibilities of where our species would go, based on where it has come from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book is a very well researched and fascinating read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Score: $\large{\frac{4.5}{5}}$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/I/51xwPegEzlL._SX333_BO1,204,203,200_.jpg&#34;&gt;Cover Image Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sydney Students School Shkreli?</title>
      <link>https://sciexpln.github.io/2016/12/03/sydney-students-school-shkreli</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 20:45:09 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sciexpln.github.io/2016/12/03/sydney-students-school-shkreli</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Setting aside the obvious alliteration in the title of this post, here
is another instance of scientific misreporting and over exaggeration.
While the effects of this kind of misreporting are much less severe than
claiming actual pseudo-scientific mumbo-jumbo, it still contributes to
the spread of misinformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Shkreli&#34;&gt;Martin Skhreli&lt;/a&gt;, also
known as the &lt;em&gt;Pharma Bro&lt;/em&gt;, is a hedge fund executive who, as the CEO of
Turing Pharmacuticals, was responsible for Turing&amp;rsquo;s acquisition of a
drug, Daraprim, an antibiotic used to treat, among other things,
infections in pregnant women, as well as AIDS and cancer patients, and for
subsequently jacking up it&amp;rsquo;s price from $\$13.50$ to $\$750$ per tablet.
This led to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Shkreli#Daraprim_price_hike_controversy&#34;&gt;widespread
condemnation&lt;/a&gt; from the media, as well as
politicians, including [then] potential presidential candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, however, a group of high school students from Sydney,
Australia synthesized the drug for a measly $\$2$ per tablet. As a high
school science project, I think this is a fantastic achievement. This
chemistry is way beyond anything I was capable of, or had resources to
try, during high school. The media narrative, however, is that this
group of high school students somehow managed to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.smh.com.au/technology/sci-tech/sydney-schoolboys-take-down-martin-shkreli-the-most-hated-man-in-the-world-20161125-gsxcu5.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;take
down&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;
or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wired.com/2016/12/internet-week-98/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;school&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; Martin
Shkreli. This is another example of the media using sensationalizing
titles for clickbait, wildly exaggerating the novelty, as well as the
potential impact of this particular (albeit successful) experiment, on
this particular problem. Shkreli himself took to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MartinShkreli/status/804406960259006464&#34;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;
to point out that this story was being overblown. However, the ever
reliable
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.snopes.com/2016/12/03/children-synthesize-two-dollar-version-of-martin-shkrelis-750-malaria-drug/&#34;&gt;Snopes&lt;/a&gt;
has a very good detailed analysis of what the actual level of
achievement this particular experiment is, in the grander scheme of
things. &lt;a href=&#34;http://arstechnica.com/science/2016/12/the-dangers-of-thinking-australian-high-school-kids-just-schooled-shkreli/&#34;&gt;Ars
technica&lt;/a&gt;
has also pointed out the issues in thinking that these were some child
prodigy scientists making some unfathomable discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pharmaceutical industry has an army of chemists with PhDs, a lot of
whom would be in a position to peform the same chemistry the high school
students did. The Snopes article also links to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/OpenSourceMalaria/OSM_To_Do_List/issues/374&#34;&gt;multiple issues and
rounds of trial and
error&lt;/a&gt;
the high school students faced in their quest to performing this
synthesis, which required help from trained laboratory technicians. All of
Snopes, Ars Technica and Shkreli himself also point out the many
additional stages and layers of complexity to go from a molecule
synthesis in a test-tube at a laboratory scale, to a commercial
production at an industrial scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all these things in perspective, it is essential to realize that
while the high school students of Sydney Grammar have performed a great
experiment in the context of their education and their curriculum, it is
nowhere close to a break through, or something path-breaking, which
would, in any way alleviate the problem of high Daraprim prices in the
United States.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>People Absorb Energy?!</title>
      <link>https://sciexpln.github.io/2016/11/26/people-absorb-energy</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 23:04:14 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sciexpln.github.io/2016/11/26/people-absorb-energy</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sciexpln.github.io/images/universe-man-energy.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;People Absorb Energy?!&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In what has to be an absolute masterclass in obfuscating science to
peddle woo, a website called &lt;em&gt;Simple Capacity&lt;/em&gt; has gone and hijacked a legitimate scientific
study to claim new-age mumbo jumbo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual Nature Communications (a very highly respected scientific
journal) &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/articles/ncomms2210&#34;&gt;paper they cite&lt;/a&gt; is a study of algae that display some parasitic
behaviour, using enzymes to digest cellulose from other nearby flora in
addtion to their own photosynthesis for generating energy. I&amp;rsquo;m not a
plant biologist, so while this may be a novel development in the field
(and from what I just read about this, it looks like it is), there is
nothing unimaginable here. Many forms of fungi and bacteria were known
to digest cellulose. In an attempt to mimic these natural cellulases, an
attempt to artificially design cellulose consuming enzymes to use in the
production of biofuels has been a target of quite a lot of recent
research in the protein engineering field. So the discovery of algae
which have this property is quite a useful step in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What psychologist and &amp;ldquo;energy healer&amp;rdquo; (whatever that is) Dr. Olivia
Bader-Lee somehow magically interprets from this in &lt;a href=&#34;http://simplecapacity.com/2016/08/science-confirms-people-absorb-energy-others/&#34;&gt;this
article&lt;/a&gt;
 [I really don&amp;rsquo;t want to give them any more clicks, but it is
impossible to make this point without linking the article] is that this
fact implies that &amp;ldquo;Human physical bodies are like sponges, soaking up
the environment&amp;rdquo;. Dr. Bader-Lee says “This is exactly why there are
certain people who feel uncomfortable in specific group settings where
there is a mix of energy and emotions”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow, the discovery of certain enzymes, actual chemical entities
which catalyze the breakdown of cellulase in algae, translates, in Dr.
Bader-Lee&amp;rsquo;s mind, into &amp;ldquo;humans can absorb energy from the surroundings&amp;rdquo;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To further quote the article,
&amp;ldquo;Bader-Lee suggests that the field of bioenergy is now ever evolving and
that studies on the plant and animal world will soon translate and
demonstrate what energy metaphysicians have known all along — that
humans can heal each other simply through energy transfer just as plants
do. “Human can absorb and heal through other humans, animals, and any
part of nature. That’s why being around nature is often uplifting and
energizing for so many people,” she concluded.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While a lot of people are rightly suspicious of something that looks
like outright magic, claims by people like Dr. Bader-Lee, which are a
bit more subtle, aren&amp;rsquo;t met by the same level of skepticism. Which might
make these claims just as much as, if not more counter to the actual
process of genuine science as claims of magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pixabay.com/en/universe-person-silhouette-star-1044107/&#34;&gt;Cover Image
Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>https://sciexpln.github.io/2016/11/26/introduction</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 22:46:45 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sciexpln.github.io/2016/11/26/introduction</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Science is interesting. Very. However, it has long lacked popular appeal. It has just not been eyecatching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, however, is rapidly changing. From eminent scientists and science popularizers like &lt;a href=&#34;https://richarddawkins.net/&#34;&gt;Prof. Richard Dawkins&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.haydenplanetarium.org/tyson/&#34;&gt;Dr. Neil deGrasse Tyson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://krauss.faculty.asu.edu/&#34;&gt;Prof. Lawrence Krauss&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apolloschildren.com/&#34;&gt;Prof. Brian Cox&lt;/a&gt; to an army of internet activists for science like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scibabe.com/&#34;&gt;SciBabe&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/BasicBiologyBabe/&#34;&gt;BiologyBabe&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ascienceenthusiast.com/&#34;&gt;A Science Enthusiast&lt;/a&gt; and many more, lots of people are working to making science fun and interesting, as well a clearing up a lot of misinformation floating around on the internet about various aspects of science and technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As not only a student of science but also a big fan of the scientific enterprise, I would like to add my two bits to the spread of awareness or science, whether it be discussing an interesting popular science book, a new interesting scientific discovery reported in the newspaper, or even combating the deluge of pseudo-science online. This website is a result of that effort. Any feedback would be greatly appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>