<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Post-rsses on The Scientific Explanation</title>
    <link>https://sciexpln.github.io/post/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Post-rsses on The Scientific Explanation</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Powered by [Hugo](//gohugo.io). Theme by [PPOffice](http://github.com/ppoffice).</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 20:45:09 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://sciexpln.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Sydney Students School Shkreli?</title>
      <link>https://sciexpln.github.io/2016/12/03/sydney-students-school-shkreli</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 20:45:09 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sciexpln.github.io/2016/12/03/sydney-students-school-shkreli</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Setting aside the obvious alliteration in the title of this post, here
is another instance of scientific misreporting and over exaggeration.
While the effects of this kind of misreporting are much less severe than
claiming actual pseudo-scientific mumbo-jumbo, it still contributes to
the spread of misinformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Shkreli&#34;&gt;Martin Skhreli&lt;/a&gt;, also
known as the &lt;em&gt;Pharma Bro&lt;/em&gt;, is a hedge fund executive who, as the CEO of
Turing Pharmacuticals, was responsible for Turing&amp;rsquo;s acquisition of a
drug, Daraprim, an antibiotic used to treat, among other things,
infections in pregnant women, as well as AIDS and cancer patients, and for
subsequently jacking up it&amp;rsquo;s price from $\$13.50$ to $\$750$ per tablet.
This led to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Shkreli#Daraprim_price_hike_controversy&#34;&gt;widespread
condemnation&lt;/a&gt; from the media, as well as
politicians, including [then] potential presidential candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, however, a group of high school students from Sydney,
Australia synthesized the drug for a measly $\$2$ per tablet. As a high
school science project, I think this is a fantastic achievement. This
chemistry is way beyond anything I was capable of, or had resources to
try, during high school. The media narrative, however, is that this
group of high school students somehow managed to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.smh.com.au/technology/sci-tech/sydney-schoolboys-take-down-martin-shkreli-the-most-hated-man-in-the-world-20161125-gsxcu5.html&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;take
down&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wired.com/2016/12/internet-week-98/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;school&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Martin
Shkreli. This is another example of the media using sensationalizing
titles for clickbait, wildly exaggerating the novelty, as well as the
potential impact of this particular (albeit successful) experiment, on
this particular problem. Shkreli himself took to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MartinShkreli/status/804406960259006464&#34;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;
to point out that this story was being overblown. However, the ever
reliable
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.snopes.com/2016/12/03/children-synthesize-two-dollar-version-of-martin-shkrelis-750-malaria-drug/&#34;&gt;Snopes&lt;/a&gt;
has a very good detailed analysis of what the actual level of
achievement this particular experiment is, in the grander scheme of
things. &lt;a href=&#34;http://arstechnica.com/science/2016/12/the-dangers-of-thinking-australian-high-school-kids-just-schooled-shkreli/&#34;&gt;Ars
technica&lt;/a&gt;
has also pointed out the issues in thinking that these were some child
prodigy scientists making some unfathomable discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pharmaceutical industry has an army of chemists with PhDs, a lot of
whom would be in a position to peform the same chemistry the high school
students did. The Snopes article also links to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/OpenSourceMalaria/OSM_To_Do_List/issues/374&#34;&gt;multiple issues and
rounds of trial and
error&lt;/a&gt;
the high school students faced in their quest to performing this
synthesis, which required help from trained laboratory technicians. All of
Snopes, Ars Technica and Shkreli himself also point out the many
additional stages and layers of complexity to go from a molecule
synthesis in a test-tube at a laboratory scale, to a commercial
production at an industrial scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all these things in perspective, it is essential to realize that
while the high school students of Sydney Grammar have performed a great
experiment in the context of their education and their curriculum, it is
nowhere close to a break through, or something path-breaking, which
would, in any way alleviate the problem of high Daraprim prices in the
United States.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>People Absorb Energy?!</title>
      <link>https://sciexpln.github.io/2016/11/26/people-absorb-energy</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 23:04:14 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sciexpln.github.io/2016/11/26/people-absorb-energy</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sciexpln.github.io/images/universe-man-energy.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;People Absorb Energy?!&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In what has to be an absolute masterclass in obfuscating science to
peddle woo, a website called &lt;em&gt;Simple Capacity&lt;/em&gt; has gone and hijacked a legitimate scientific
study to claim new-age mumbo jumbo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual Nature Communications (a very highly respected scientific
journal) &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/articles/ncomms2210&#34;&gt;paper they cite&lt;/a&gt; is a study of algae that display some parasitic
behaviour, using enzymes to digest cellulose from other nearby flora in
addtion to their own photosynthesis for generating energy. I&amp;rsquo;m not a
plant biologist, so while this may be a novel development in the field
(and from what I just read about this, it looks like it is), there is
nothing unimaginable here. Many forms of fungi and bacteria were known
to digest cellulose. In an attempt to mimic these natural cellulases, an
attempt to artificially design cellulose consuming enzymes to use in the
production of biofuels has been a target of quite a lot of recent
research in the protein engineering field. So the discovery of algae
which have this property is quite a useful step in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What psychologist and &amp;ldquo;energy healer&amp;rdquo; (whatever that is) Dr. Olivia
Bader-Lee somehow magically interprets from this in &lt;a href=&#34;http://simplecapacity.com/2016/08/science-confirms-people-absorb-energy-others/&#34;&gt;this
article&lt;/a&gt;
 [I really don&amp;rsquo;t want to give them any more clicks, but it is
impossible to make this point without linking the article] is that this
fact implies that &amp;ldquo;Human physical bodies are like sponges, soaking up
the environment&amp;rdquo;. Dr. Bader-Lee says “This is exactly why there are
certain people who feel uncomfortable in specific group settings where
there is a mix of energy and emotions”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow, the discovery of certain enzymes, actual chemical entities
which catalyze the breakdown of cellulase in algae, translates, in Dr.
Bader-Lee&amp;rsquo;s mind, into &amp;ldquo;humans can absorb energy from the surroundings&amp;rdquo;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To further quote the article,
&amp;ldquo;Bader-Lee suggests that the field of bioenergy is now ever evolving and
that studies on the plant and animal world will soon translate and
demonstrate what energy metaphysicians have known all along — that
humans can heal each other simply through energy transfer just as plants
do. “Human can absorb and heal through other humans, animals, and any
part of nature. That’s why being around nature is often uplifting and
energizing for so many people,” she concluded.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While a lot of people are rightly suspicious of something that looks
like outright magic, claims by people like Dr. Bader-Lee, which are a
bit more subtle, aren&amp;rsquo;t met by the same level of skepticism. Which might
make these claims just as much as, if not more counter to the actual
process of genuine science as claims of magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pixabay.com/en/universe-person-silhouette-star-1044107/&#34;&gt;Cover Image
Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>https://sciexpln.github.io/2016/11/26/introduction</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 22:46:45 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sciexpln.github.io/2016/11/26/introduction</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of misinformation floating around on the internet,
including misinformation about various aspects of science and
technology. From eminent scientists and science popularizers like &lt;a href=&#34;https://richarddawkins.net/&#34;&gt;Prof.
Richard Dawkins&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.haydenplanetarium.org/tyson/&#34;&gt;Dr. Neil deGrasse
Tyson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://krauss.faculty.asu.edu/&#34;&gt;Prof. Lawrence
Krauss&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apolloschildren.com/&#34;&gt;Prof. Brian Cox&lt;/a&gt; to an army of internet activists for science like
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scibabe.com/&#34;&gt;SciBabe&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/BasicBiologyBabe/&#34;&gt;BiologyBabe&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ascienceenthusiast.com/&#34;&gt;A Science
Enthusiast&lt;/a&gt; and many more, a lot of
scientists and engineers are speaking out against pseudoscience. As not
only a student of science but also a big fan of the scientific
enterprise, I would like to add my two bits to the spread of awareness
and combating the deluge of pseudo-science online. This website is a
result of that effort.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>